Register of the Irwin Abrams Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Irwin Abrams papers
1900-2005
83025
Hoover Institution Archives
38 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (16.1 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, minutes, bulletins, newsletters, curricular material, and other printed matter, relating to activities of the American Friends Service Committee, international volunteer work camps, conscientious objection during World War II, education in Germany, international educational and cultural exchanges, especially between the United States and East and West Germany, and the Nobel Peace Prize.
Abrams, Irwin, 1914-2010
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Irwin Abrams Papers, Swarthmore College Peace Collection
Biographical Note
1914, February 24 Born, San Francisco, California
1934 B.A., Stanford University
1935 M.A., Harvard University
1938 Ph.D., Harvard University
1938-1943 Instructor, Department of History, Stanford University
1943-1946 Director of Training, American Friends Service Committee (AFSC)
1946-1947 Director, Quaker Overseas Work Camps (AFSC)
1947-1949 Assistant Professor, Department of History, Antioch University
1949-1951 Associate Professor, Department of History, Antioch University
1951-1979 Professor, Department of History, Antioch University
1953 Specialist, Exchange Program, U.S. State Department, Germany
1955-1971 Member, Board of Directors, Antioch Review
1956-1957 Chairman, International Student Seminars, AFSC, Switzerland and Yugoslavia
1956-1964 Educational Director, Shipboard Programs of Council on Student Travel
1961 Fulbright Lecturer, University of Cologne, Germany
1964 Chairman, International Student Seminars, AFSC, Hungary
1965-1967 Director, Great Lakes Colleges Association (GLCA) Seminars, Yugoslavia
1970 Co-director, GLCA Seminars
1970-1973 Member, Board of Directors, Council on International Educational Exchange
1972 Coordinator, Curriculum Materials Team, GLCA Seminars
1972-1975 Director, GLCA-Antioch European Team in Comparative Urban Studies
1976 Co-director, Task Force on International Education of International City Management Association
1976-1978 Vice president, International Society for Educational, Cultural and Scientific Interchanges (ISECSI)
1978-1982 President, ISECSI
1979 Co-chairman, Project on International Exchange Research of German Academic Exchange Service and ISECSI
1979-1981 Distinguished University Professor, Antioch University
1981- Distinguished University Professor Emeritus, Antioch University
1988 Author, The Nobel Peace Prize and the Laureates, 1901-1987
1990 Editor, Worlds of Peace
Scope and Content of Collection
The Irwin Abrams papers contain speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, minutes, bulletins, newsletters, curricular material, and other printed matter related to activities of the American Friends Service Committee, international volunteer work camps, conscientious objection during World War II, education in Germany, international educational and cultural exchanges, especially between the United States and East and West Germany, and the Nobel Peace Prize.
Irwin Abrams, a peace scholar and historian, influenced the field of peace studies from the beginning of his career. In 1936, Abrams traveled to Europe to do research for his dissertation, A History of European Peace Societies, 1867-1899. Although the dissertation won the Charles Sumner Peace Prize in 1938 and was often quoted by scholars, the paper was never published in its entirety.
As a Quaker, pacifist, and conscientious objector during World War II, Abrams was committed to fostering peace through relief work and educational exchange programs. He wrote, "I became convinced that to change the world you had to change yourself." During World War II, Abrams left his teaching position at Stanford to work with the American Friends Service Committee, where he served as Director of Training from 1943 to 1946 and directed relief work camps in Europe from 1946 to 1947. The American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) File contains correspondence, diaries, memoranda, bulletins, and notes related to relief work and conscientious objectors. Of note are two travel diaries from AFSC missions--one from 1946 documenting volunteer work camps to rebuild after World War II, the other from a 1963 mission to Germany, where AFSC members visited East and West Berlin, as well as other parts of Germany, shortly after the construction of the Berlin Wall. The 1963 journal includes notes on meetings with government officials.
Throughout his career, Abrams wrote about issues of peace. After the publication of The Nobel Peace Prize and the Laureates, 1901-1987, Abrams became known as a leading authority on the subject. Throughout his life, he met many of the peace laureates, including the Dalai Lama, Desmond Tutu, Willy Brandt, Jimmy Carter, Jose Ramos-Horta, and Martin Luther King, Jr. The collection includes Abrams' Speeches and Writings on peace, ethics, and educational exchange programs. See also Incremental Materials for speeches and writings from the 1990s and 2000s.
In 1981, Abrams interviewed Adolf Ciborowski, Chief Architect of Warsaw, who helped rebuild the city after World War II. A recording of this interview is available in the Sound Recordings. Please note that a use copy is available.
In addition to being a peace scholar and professor, Abrams collected materials related to peace and international education. Over the years, Abrams sent many increments of materials to his collection at the Hoover Institution Archives. A large group of these materials was processed in 2017. The Incremental Materials are arranged in nine groups, some of which are continuations of series in the original accession of materials.
Within the Incremental Materials, the Academic Career and Peace Organizations File documents Abrams' work as a history professor, peace scholar, and advocate for peace. His work in academia often overlapped with his commitment to creating a more peaceful world, which is perhaps most clearly exemplified by his involvement with study abroad programs. This file includes correspondence, reports, notes, and evaluations related to Abrams' teaching career at Stanford University and Antioch College, his involvement in educational exchange groups, and materials related to his work for peace organizations. See also the Subject File of the original accession for more material related to Abrams' work with peace organizations, educational exchange programs with the Great Lakes College Association, and Antioch College international education programs.
These materials also include a variety of printed matter related to peace and international education, including World War II era pamphlets.
American Friends Service Committee.; Education--Germany.; Education.; Germany (East)--Relations--United States.; Germany (West)--Relations--United States.; Germany.; Intellectual cooperation.; International education.; Nobel Prizes.; Peace.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Relations--Germany (East); United States--Relations--Germany (West); Volunteer workers in community development.; Work camps.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscientious objectors.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1932-1988. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Curricula vitae and articles arranged chronologically. See also Incremental Materials.
  - Curricula vitae, correspondence, and one article (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Speeches and Writings, 1938-1989
  Typescript, and printed speeches and articles by Irwin Abrams arranged chronologically by date of publication or presentation. See also Incremental Materials.
  - "The Nobel Peace Prize and the Laureates: An Illustrated Biographical History, 1901-1987," Printed copy (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - "A History of European Peace Societies, 1867-1899," Doctoral dissertation. Printed summary, 1938. (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "I Believe," The Friend, Ninth Month 19. Printed copy, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "The Austrian Question at the Turn of the Twentieth Century," Journal of Central European Affairs, Printed copy, 1944 July. (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Summary of speech, International Conference of Peace Workers, Includes correspondence with Cornelius Kruse and Ray Newton. Typescript, 1946 September 13. (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "To the Seeker," Friends Intelligencer, First Month 29. Printed copy, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - "Less than a Riddle," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1951 Summer. (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - "My System of Values," Friends Intelligencer, Seventh Month 4. Printed copy, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "The Struggle for Poland," Yale Law Journal, Review of H. Peter Stern, The Struggle for Poland. Printed copy, 1954 March. (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "Western Survival," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1955 Spring. (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Grappling with History," Antioch Notes, Printed copy, 1955 September. (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - "The Historian's Craft and General Education," The Journal of General Education, Printed copy, 1955 October. (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "An Alpine View of Neutrality," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1957 Spring. (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - "What's Missing on the Campus?" Antioch Review, Printed copies, including revised version, 1957 May. (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - "The American Abroad: An Introduction," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1958 Winter. (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "Reflections on the End of an Era," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1959 Winter. (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Study Abroad, Number 6 in New Dimensions in Higher Education Series, United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Printed copy, 1960. (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - "Foreign Travel Plus," Antioch Notes, Printed copy, 1960 September. (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "Overseas Travel-Study Programs in U.S. Higher Education," Current Issues in Higher Education, Printed copy, 1961. (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - "Einige Bemerkungen zu Material uber die Vereinigten Staaten in einer Auswahl von Lehrbuchern deutscher Gymnasien," Summary of speech, 4th Amerikanisch-deutschen Tagung Braunschweig. Printed copy, 1961 June 27-July 1. (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "American Influences Abroad: A Preface," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1962 Summer. (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - "A Different Kind of Discipline," Overseas, Printed copy, 1963 May. (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - "Invitation to Explore America," Introductory lecture, International Work-Study Program, Antioch College, Printed copy, 1964 April 6. (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - "Why Study Abroad?" Speech, National Association for Foreign Student Affairs, Philadelphia. Printed copy, 1965 April 30-May 1. (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - "The Student Abroad," Higher Education: Some Newer Developments, Printed copy, 1965. (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - "The Educated Traveler," Antioch Notes, Printed copy, 1965 March. (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - "Study Abroad as Humanist Learning--The Promise of International Educational Exchange," Speech, International Seminar "University Today," Dubrovnik, Yugoslavia. Typescript, 1965 July. (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - "The Bolshevik Revolution: Fifty Years After," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1967/1968 Winter. (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - "The Evolution of Undergraduate Study Programs Abroad," International Education and Cultural Exchange, Printed copy, 1968 Spring. (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - "Interinstitutional Cooperation in International Studies," Liberal Education, Printed copy, 1968 March. (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - "American-Yugoslav Seminar: A Cooperative Adventure," International Education and Cultural Exchange, Printed copy, 1968 Fall. (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - "A Man of Noble Purpose and Great Luck," Chicago Sun Times, Printed copy, 1970 December 20. (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - "American Architecture Comes of Age: European Reaction to H. H. Richardson and Louis Sullivan," The Journal of American History, Printed copy, 1973 September. (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - "Notes on the Evaluation of Programs in International and Intellectual Education," Prepared for the ACE Task Force on Diffusion of International Studies. Printed copy, 1974 March 30. (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - "Urban Planning in Poland Today," AIP Journal, Printed copy, 1975 July. (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - We Can Learn from Europe's Cities, Printed copy. Includes handwritten notes, 1976. (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - "A Consortium at Work in the World: The Great Lakes Colleges Association in Yugoslavia," International/Intercultural Education in the Four-Year College: A Handbook on Strategies for Change, Printed copy, 1977. (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - "An International Project for Urban Administrators," Speech, International Studies Association, St. Louis, Typescript, 1977. (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Evaluating Academic Programs Abroad: The CIEE Project, Printed copy, 1978 February. (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - "Working into Another Culture," Antioch Notes, Printed copy, 1978 March. (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - "Beyond Experience: The Experiential Approach to Cross-Cultural Education," Cross Currents, Printed copy, 1979. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "The Impact of Antioch Education Through Experience Abroad," Alternative Higher Education, Printed copy, 1979. (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "What's in a Name?" ISECSI Bulletin, Printed copy, 1979 January. (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Notes on the Visit of Professor Irwin Abrams to the Federal Republic on the Invitation of the German Academic Exchange Service," 1979. Printed copy, May 22 to June 1, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "Cross Cultural Experiential Education," The Newsletter of Interversitas, Printed copy, 1979 September/October. (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Noble Aims for Social Change," Antioch College Record, Printed copy, 1980 May 24. (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Von der Theorie zur Praxis," DAAD, Printed copy, 1980 November. (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "Some Reflections on Historical Research and International Interchange," Speech, Conference on Research on International Exchange, Bonn, Federal Republic of Germany. Typescript, 1980 November 24-28. (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Study Abroad as Cultural Exploration," New Directions for Experiential Learning, Printed copy, 1981. (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "The DAAD-ISECSI Conference at Bonn: A summary," World Higher Education COMMUNIQUE, Printed copy, 1981 Summer. (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - "The Challenge of Historic Preservation," Speech, 14th Congress, International Union of Architects, Warsaw, Poland. Typescript, 1981 June 15-21. (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "The University Professor as Teacher: Some Reflections on the American Experience," Speech, 27th Session, International Seminar "University Today," Dubrovnik, Yugoslavia, and Univerzitet Dana, Belgrade., 1982 August 29-September 2. (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - "Wingspread: Spanning the Atlantic," World Higher Education COMMUNIQUE, Printed copy, 1982. (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - "Lessons of the First German-American Exchange Professorships," Speech, Joint meeting of the International Studies Association and the ISECSI, Ohio. Typescript, 1982 March 25-26. (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Friends and the Seeker, Printed copy, 1983. (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "Enhancing the Traveler's Visual Awareness," Speech, Annual Conference of the National Association for Foreign Student Affairs, Ohio. Typescript, 1983 May 24-27. (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - "The Opening Word," Speech, Antioch College Commencement. Typescript, 1983 June 25. (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - "John W. Burgess, Theodore Roosevelt Professor in Berlin, 1906-1907: A Case Study in Educational Exchange," Educational Biography, Printed copy, 1983 Fall. (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - "The Transformation of the Nobel Peace Prize," Speech, Annual convention, International Studies Association, Atlanta, Georgia. Typescript, 1984 March 28. (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - "Reminiscences of an Orienter," Speech, International Society for Educational, Cultural, and Scientific Interchanges. Printed copy, 1984 November 4. (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - "Red October: The Bolshevik Revolution of 1917," Unitarian Universalist World, Review of Robert Daniels, Red October: The Bolshevik Revolution of 1917. Printed copy, 1984 December. (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - "Quaker Distinctives: Are They Still Relevant?" Seventh Annual Conference, Friends Association for Higher Education. Printed copy, 1986 June 20-24. (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - "The Nobel Peace Prize--Has it Made A Difference?" Speech, Annual convention, International Studies Association, Washington D.C. Typescript, 1987 April 16. (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - "Friends: One Quaker's Perspective on Spirituality," Yellow Springs News, Printed copy, 1986 March 12. (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - "A Word About Listening," Friends Journal, Proof copy, 1987 June 1/15. (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Report from the Committee on Quaker Studies on Human Betterment, Eighth Annual Conference, Friends Association for Higher Education, Printed copy, 1987 June 26-30. (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - "Behind the Scenes: The Nobel Committee and Oscar Arias," The Antioch Review, Printed copy, 1988 Summer. (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - "Christian L. Lange: Forgotten Nobel Prize Winner?" The Norseman, Printed copy, 1988 November. (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - "The Prize for the United Nations Peacekeepers," The Nobel Prize Annual 1988. Typescript, 1989 January 1. (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - "Tenzin Gyatso, The Fourteenth Dalai Lama of Tibet," for the 3rd printing of The Nobel Peace Prize and the Laureates, Typescript, 1989. (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - "Carl von Ossietzky and the First Nobel Peace Prize for Human Rights," Speech, Joint Annual Convention of the British International Studies Association and the International Studies Association, London, United Kingdom. Printed copy, 1989 March 28-April 1. (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Speech, Antioch Alumni Reunion, Typescript, 1989 June 29. (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - "Service and Involvement," Quakershaker Yellow Springs Friends Meeting. Typescript, 1989 August. (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - "World Can Learn from Dalai Lama's Example," Dayton Daily News, Printed copy, 1989 October 20. (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Summary of speech, International Conference of Peace Workers, Geneva, Switzerland, Typescript, 1946 September 12-14. (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "A Story 'Too Good to be True" - Yet It Is," Yellow Spring News, Printed copy, 1990 January 17. (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Book reviews, Friends Journal and The Antioch Review, Printed copies, 1990 summer. (Box-folder 13: 7)
- American Friends Service Committee (AFSC), 1938-1984 (Boxes 2-4)
  Correspondence, reports, notes, memoranda, articles diary, and printed matter documenting Irwin Abrams' participation in AFSC activities
  - European trip to AFSC Work Camps, Typescript diary, 1946 July-December. (Box-folder 2: 27)
    See also Box 16, Folder 8.
  - World Youth Forum, Moscow, Soviet Union Communique, reports, and notes, 1961 July 25-August 3. (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Quaker Mission to Germany, 1963 September 8-30
    - General. Memoranda, bulletins, and notes, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2: 29)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2: 30)
    - Diary, 1963 September 8-30
      - Preliminary draft (Box-folder 2: 31)
      - Final draft (Box-folder 2: 32)
    - Printed matter. Clippings, pamphlets, and leaflets, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2: 33)
    - Reports
      - General, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2: 34)
      - Journey Through A Wall. Printed copy. Includes notes, reports, memoranda, and correspondence with Roland Warren and others, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Conference on Ideology and Human Encounters, AFSC Public Meeting, Philadephia, Correspondence, leaflets, newsletters, notes, memoranda, and reports, 1964 October 23-24. (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Liaison Office of International Work Camps (coordinating body for various European and American organizations including QIVS, the parent organization of American and European AFSC branches). Bulletins, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Quaker International Voluntary Service (member of the Liaison Office of International Work Camps and parent organization of American and European AFSC branches)
    - General. Pamphlets and other printed matter, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1953 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Minutes of QIVS meetings, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Questionnaire. Includes summary of responses, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Reports, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Service Civil International (a non-profit organization promoting peace through voluntary participation in self-supporting projects). Articles, minutes, and newsletters, 1947-1984 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Subject file, 1939-1983
    - Atlantic Charter. Article and report, 1941 and 1983 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Conscientious objectors
      - General. Printed matter, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 3: 9)
      - Civilian Peace Service. Pamphlets, memoranda, and newsletters, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 3: 10)
      - National Council for Conscientious Objectors. Printed matter, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - National Service Board for Religious Objectors. Press releases, memoranda, and newsletters, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Student Peace Service. Pamphlets and correspondence, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Domestic work camps. Pamphlets, newsletters, and manuals, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Peace. Pamphlets and correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Refugees. Bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Relief
      - General. Handbood and bulletins, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - China. Bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Clothing. Pamphlets, guides, and bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - England. Pamphlets and bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - France. Pamphlets and bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Miscellaneous. Pamphlets, correspondence, and articles, 1940-1967 (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Subject File, 1902-1987 (Boxes 4-13)
  Pamphlets, reports, notes, memoranda, clippings, and printed matter arranged alphabetically by subject. See also Incremental Materials
  - Association for the Social Scientific Study of International Problems (Sozialwissenschaftlicher Studienkreis fur Internationale Probleme). Reports, statement of purpose, and reading list, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Carl-Duisberg-Gesellschaft fur Nachwuchsfvrderung e.V. Reports, 1959 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - International education
    - Antioch International Education Programs, 1959-1975
      - General. Mimeographed materials, memoranda, and articles, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 4: 12)
      - Notes. European journey, Typewritten and mimeographed copies, 1960 June 9-July 21. (Box-folder 4: 13)
      - Pamphlets, Printed copies, 1963-1975. (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Council for the Advancement of Experiential Learning and International Relations Program of Michigan State University, Task Force, "The Role of Experiential Learning in Cross Cultural Program,", 1978-1979
      - General. Definition and purpose statements, notes, and mailing list, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 15)
      - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 4: 16)
      - Memoranda, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 5: 1)